Guide to the Adnan Pachachi book collection AD.MC.085
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Adnan Pachachi book collection
1911-2014
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Pachachi, Adnan, 1923-2019
AD.MC.085
46 Volumes
Consists of selected books and other publications from the personal library of Adnan al-Pachachi (1923-2019), an Iraqi politician and diplomat who also served as an adviser to the government of the United Arab Emirates. Collection includes titles inscribed to Pachachi from their authors, usually pertaining to the history and current affairs of Iraq or the United Arab Emirates, or titles otherwise related to the life and career of Pachachi and his family.
Conditions governing access
Collection is open for use in the Archives and Special Collections Reading Room, New York University Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Collection donated by the Estate of Adnan Pachachi, October 2020.
Arrangement
Titles are arranged in three categories: Iraq, United Arab Emirates, and General. Within those categories, they are alphabetized by author. Pending full bibliographic cataloging of each title, volume numbers have been assigning in this finding aid, in order to locate them.
Biographical note
Adnan al-Pachachi was born in 14 May 1923 in Baghdad, into a politically active Sunni family. His father, Muzahim Amin al-Pachachi, served as Prime Minister of Iraq in 1948-1949, his uncle Hamdi al-Pachachi served as both Prime Minister (1944-1946) and Foreign Minister (1948) of Iraq; and his cousin Nadim al-Pachachi served as Secretary-General of OPEC (1971-1972).
Pachachi was educated at Victoria College, Alexandria, where he was initially drawn to Arab nationalist political movements; and received a degree in political science from American University in Beirut in 1943. From 1950-1958 he served in the Political Department of the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs, but was removed due to his support of Egyptian nationalist leader Gamel Abdel Nasser. Following the 1958 revolution in Iraq, he was appointed by the Qassim regime to serve as the Permanent Representative of Iraq to the United Nations in 1959, a post in which he served for much of the next decade. During this period, he also served from 1965-1967 as Foreign Minister of Iraq, during which time he was vocal in his support of Palestinian rights and his opposition to Israel during the Six-Day War in 1967.
Following the coup that brought Saddam Hussein to power in Iraq, Pachachi went into exile in 1969, moving to the Emirate of Abu Dhabi, and began serving as a counselor to the Emirate's leader, Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al-Nahyan, who appointed him a Minister of State in July 1971. Following the formation of the United Arab Emirates in December 1971, Pachachi played a key role in paving the way for the new country's admittance to the United Nations.
After the U.S. invasion of Iraq and overthrow of Saddam Hussein in 2003, Pachachi returned to Iraq, initially to serve in the Iraq Governing Council, where he was a vocal critic of the U.S. actions and policies within the country. In 2005 he participated in the first legislative elections, heading the Assembly of Independent Democrats, and subsequently served in the National Assembly. In 2010, he stood as a candidate again with Ayad Allawi's Iraqi List, but by 2011 had grown increasingly pessimistic about the chances for a secular democracy in Iraq, and returned to Abu Dhabi.
Adnan Pachachi died in Abu Dhabi at the age of 96 on 17 November 2019.
[source: Wikipedia article, "Adnan Pachachi," https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adnan_Pachachi, accessed 13 May 2021].
Content Description
The Adnan Pachachi collection consists of selected books and other publications from the personal library of Adnan al-Pachachi (1923-2019), former Iraqi foreign minister and adviser to the government of the United Arab Emirates. The collection includes titles inscribed to Pachachi from their authors, usually pertaining to the history and current affairs of Iraq or the United Arab Emirates, or titles otherwise related to the life and career of Pachachi and his family.
The books in this collection were selected from the library in his home in Abu Dhabi. Selections were made on the basis of subject matter of the titles, and in particular how these titles appeared to have related to Pachachi's own lived experience, both as a political figure from Iraq, as well as his role as a long-time resident of Abu Dhabi and adviser to the rulers of that Emirate, and of the United Arab Emirates.
A substantial portion of this collection consist of presentation copies inscribed to Pachachi from their authors. Many of these consist of memoirs, historical works, literary titles, and works on current affairs and politics, mostly from Iraqi authors and pertaining to Iraq. Additional works about the history and culture of the United Arab Emirates, and in particular, Abu Dhabi, are also included, with some of them being presentation copies, others consisting of works that included essays by Pachachi.
An additional group of titles not included in this collection were added to the Main Collection of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library. These consisted of works of general interest, typically about world history or the history of the Middle East, but not otherwise related to Pachachi.
Iraq -- History -- 1921-; Iraq -- History -- 2003-; Iraq -- Politics and government -- History; Arabic prose literature -- Iraq; United Arab Emirates -- History -- 20th century
- Iraq titles, 1963-2014
  - ʻAbd al-Wahhāb, ʻAṭā. Al-Amīr Abd'allah: sūrah qalamīyah (Bayrūt: al-Mu assasah al-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2001) (Volume 1)
  - ʻAbd al-Wahhāb, ʻAṭā. ʻAlá hāmish (al-Sulālah): mā qālahu al-kuttāb al-ʻIrāqīyūn ʻan kitāb Sulālat al-ṭīn li-ʻAṭā ʻAbd al-Wahhāb. (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2009) (Volume 2)
  - ʻAbd al-Wahhāb, ʻAṭā. Sulālat al-ṭīn: sīrat maʼsāh / [Progeny of clay] (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2004) (Volume 3)
  - Allawi, Ali A. Iḥtilāl al-ʻIrāq: ribḥ al-ḥarb wa-khasārat al-salām (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2009) (Volume 4)
  - Aʻrajī, Ḥalīm Ḥasan ʻAbd ʻAlī. al-Shaykh Khawwām, 1881-1967: al-thāʼir-- al-insān: qiṣṣat taḥaddī al-tabʻīyah wa-al-taʻassuf fī ẓill ẓurūf al-qahr wa-al-takhalluf (Baghdad, 2002) (Volume 5)
  - Baḥrānī, Iḥsān Raʼūf. Nabaḍāt al-dhākirah: mudhakkirāt. (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2011) (Volume 6)
  - Bāqr, Farhān. Hakumī al-ḥakām min qāsim ila Saddām (Sharjah: Safi, 2012) (Volume 7)
  - Fawzī, Aḥmad. 12 ra'īs wuzarā' fī al-'ahd al-malakī (Baghdād: Yuṭlabu min Maktabat al-Fikr al-ʻArab 1984) (Volume 8)
  - Finnie, David H. Shifting lines in the sand: Kuwait's elusive frontier with Iraq (London: I.B. Tauris, 1992) (Volume 9)
  - al-Hāfidh, Mahdī. al-'Irāq: nabū'āt al-āmal (Baghdād: Dār Mīzūbūtamīya, 2013). (Volume 10)
  - Ḥanẓal, Fāliḥ. Asrār maqtal al-ʻāʼilah al-mālikah fī al-ʻIrāq: awwal ṣafḥah dāmīyah fī tārīkh al-ʻIrāq al-ḥadīth, 14 Tamūz 1958 (London: Dār al-Ḥikmah, 2008). (Volume 11)
  - Khāliṣ, Maḥmūd. Dhākirat al-waraq: sittūn ʻāman min tārīkh al-ʻIrāq al-ḥadīth fī yawmīyāt Maḥmūd Khāliṣ (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2010) (Volume 12)
  - Kirdar, Nemir. In pursuit of fulfilment: my life journey. (London: Weidenfeld & Nicolson, 2012) (Volume 13)
  - Laperruque, Cosette Marie; Murphy, Mary Alice. Return to Baghdad: an American woman's journey (Baltimore: PublishAmerica, 2003) (Volume 14)
  - Morris, James [Jan Morris]. al-Mulūk al-Hāshimīyūn (Beirut: Al-maktab al'alami al-talif wa al-tarjimah, n.d. ) (Volume 15)
  - Murūwah, Karīm. Fī al-baḥth ʻan al-mustaqbal: ḥiwār fikrī wa-siyāsī wa-shakhṣī ajratahu al-bāḥithah al-Maghribīyah Maryam Sīdī Ḥaydah (Beirut: Dār al-Sāqī, 2009) (Volume 16)
  - Murūwah, Karīm. Naḥwa nahḍah jadīdah lil-yasār fī al-ālam al-'Arabī (Bayrūt: Dār al-Sāqī, 2010) (Volume 17)
  - Safiḥāt min tārīkh al-'Irāq al-ma'āṣir, 1914-1958: mudhakirāt al farīq awal rukin Sālih Sā'ib al-Jiburī (Beirut: AlMaaref Forum, 2012). (Volume 18)
  - Shikārah, Aḥmad ʻAbd al-Razzāq. al-ʻIrāq: tadāʻīyāt mā baʻda al-intikhābāt al-barlamānīyah wa-qurb al-insiḥāb al-Amrīkī. (Abu Dhabi: Markaz al-Imārāt lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Buḥūth al-Istirātījīyah, 2011) (Volume 19)
  - Sousa, Ahmed. Fayaḍānāt Baghdād fī al-tārīkh: baḥth fī tārīkh fayaḍānāt anhur al-ʻIrāq wa-taʼthīruhā bi-al-nisbah li-madīnat Baghdād = The floods of Baghdad in history (Baghdād: Al-Adib Press, 1963-1965) (Volume 20)
  - Wardī, ʻAlī. Lamaḥāt ijtimāʻīyah min tārīkh al-ʻIrāq al-ḥadīth / Social aspects of Iraqi modern history. Vol. 4: Min ʻām 1914 ilá ʻām 1918 -- al-juzʼ (Baghdād: Maṭbaʻat al-Shaʻab, 1974). (Volume 21)
  - Wardī, ʻAlī. Lamaḥāt ijtimāʻīyah min tārīkh al-ʻIrāq al-ḥadīth / Social aspects of Iraqi modern history. Vol. 6: Min ʻām 1920 ilá ʻām 1924. (Baghdād: Maṭbaʻat al-Maʻārif, 1976). (Volume 22)
  - Al-Zaīdī, Dr. Sanān Sādiq Hussein; and Al-Jābrī, Dr. Khalīl Hamoud Uthmān. Arkān 'Ibādī: āhd ruwwād bina' al-daulah al-'irāqīyah (no publisher, no location, 2014). (Volume 23)
  - Zakī, Maʼmūn Amīn. Izdihār al-ʻIrāq taḥta al-ḥukm al-Mulukī, 1921-1958 :dirāsah tārīkhīyah, siyāsīyah, ijtimāʻīyah muqāranah (London: Dār al-Ḥikmah, 2011) (Volume 24)
  - Zaki, Saniha Amin, edited by Ellen Jawdat. Memoir of an Iraqi woman doctor [Place of publication not identified, 2014] (Volume 25)
  - Zuhdī, Zāhid Muḥammad. al-Jawāhirī: ṣannājat al-shiʻr al-ʻArabī fī al-qarn al-ʻishrīn (Beirut: Dār al Qalam, 1999). (Volume 26)
- United Arab Emirates titles, 1978-2014
  - ʻAbd Allāh, Muḥammad Mursī. The United Arab Emirates: a modern history (London: Croom Helm, 1978) (Volume 27)
  - Current transformations and their potential role in realizing change in the Arab world. (Abu Dhabi: Emirates Center for Strategic Studies and Research, 2007.) (Volume 28)
  - Dhihlī, Ibrāhīm. Abū Ẓaby: dhikrayā̄t min al-māḍī (Dawlat al-Imārāt al-ʻArabīyah al-Muttaḥidah: Kuttāb Publishing, 2014) (Volume 29)
  - Fares, Mohammed Fares. Zāyid fī al-wathā'iq al-Barītānīyah (Abu Dhabi: al-Majlis al-Watani al-'Ulum, 2008) (Volume 30)
  - Ḥanẓal, Fāliḥ. al-Mufaṣṣal fī tārīkh al-Imārāt al-ʻArabīyah al-Muttaḥidah ([Abū Ẓaby]: al-Imārāt al-ʻArabīyah al-Muttaḥidah, Lajnat al-Turāth wa-al-Tārīkh, 1983). (Volume 31)
  - Ḥammūdī, Najm al-Dīn ʻAbd Allāh. Qiyām Dawlat al-Imārāt al-ʻArabīyah al-Muttaḥidah: mudhakkirāt wa-dirāsāt (Abu Dhabi: [ʻAbd Allāh Najm al-Dīn ʻAbd Allāh Ḥammudī], 2014) (Volume 32)
  - Holton, Patricia. Mother without a mask: a Westerner's story of her Arab family (London: Motivate Pub., 1991) (Volume 33)
  - Khālīfa wa al-ta'alūn al-dawlī sahib al-sheikh Khālīfa bin Zāyid al-Nahyyān, rā'is dawlat al-Imārāt...(Abu Dhabi: Maktab na'ib rā'is majlis al-wizara' li-shu'ūn al-'ilam, 2004). (Volume 34)
  - Khalis, Dr. Walid Hamoud. Fadl al-'Arab wa-al-tanbīh 'alā 'ulūmihā (Abu Dhabi: Cultural Foundation, 1998) (Volume 35)
  - Khalis, Dr. Walid Hamoud. Sheikh Zāyid bin Sulṭān al Nahyān: dirasāt fī 'anasīr al'abda' al-sh'arī [Sheikh Zayed...a study in the elements of poetic creativity] (Oman: Sultan Qaboos University, 2002) (Volume 36)
  - Nahyan, Khalid S. Z. The three islands: mapping the UAE-Iran dispute. (London: Royal United Services Institute, 2013) (Volume 37)
  - Rashid, Noor Ali. Sheikh Zayed, life and times: through the lens of Noor Ali Rashid (Dubai, UAE: Motivate Pub., 2001). (Volume 38)
- General, 1911-2003
  - British Petroleum Company. Our industry, petroleum: petroleum: a handbook dealing with the organisation and functions of an integrated international oil company, with particular reference to the British Petroleum Company Limited. 4th edition. (London, 1970) (Volume 39)
  - Cottrell, Alvin J. The Persian Gulf States: a general survey (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1980) (Volume 40)
  - Damlūjī, Fārūq. Tārīkh al-adyān: al-ulūhīyah wa-tārīkh al-ālihah (Bayrūt: al-Ahlīyah, 2003) (Volume 41)
  - Hourani, George Fadlo. Arab seafaring in the Indian Ocean in ancient and early medieval times. (Beirut: Khayats, 1963) (Volume 42)
  - Jawdat, Nameer Ali, editor. Selected documents of the international petroleum industry 1967 (Vienna: [Information Dept.] Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries, 1968) (Volume 43)
  - Khalid bin Sultan, Prince, with Patrick Seale. Desert warrior: a personal view of the Gulf War by the Joint Forces commander (New York: HarperCollins Publishers, 1995). (Volume 44)
  - Khalis, Dr. Walid Hamoud. al-Shuʻarāʼ al-nuqqād. (Kuwait: Maktaba al Falah, 1986) (Volume 45)
  - Memorandum and articles of association of Turkish Petroleum Company, Limited (London: Bischoff, Coxe, Bishoff and Thompson, 1911) (Volume 46)